<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on jvican</title>
    <link>https://jvican.github.io/post/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on jvican</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 20 May 2018 10:00:00 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://jvican.github.io/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Using `scalac-profiling` to profile and reduce compile times of typeclass derivation</title>
      <link>https://jvican.github.io/post/scalac-profiling/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 20 May 2018 10:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jvican.github.io/post/scalac-profiling/</guid>
      <description>Today I write about how I&amp;rsquo;ve reduced compilation times of a project that uses typeclass derivation to create parsers for CLIs (command-line interfaces) with Shapeless.
Typeclass derivation makes a heavy use of macros and implicit search to reduce boilerplate and reduce code maintenance, but has a high cost on compile times.
In most of the cases, slow compilations of this common use case in the Scala community originate from either an unintentional misuse of a macro-based library, or inefficient macro implementations.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How often do we change our sbt builds</title>
      <link>https://jvican.github.io/post/git-sbt-analysis/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Oct 2017 23:29:12 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jvican.github.io/post/git-sbt-analysis/</guid>
      <description>I spend a lot of time thinking about build tools and popular setups, and what changes are more likely to impact developers positively. In one of these ramblings, one question popped up: &amp;ldquo;How often do we change our builds?&amp;rdquo;
It&amp;rsquo;s not easier to answer this question, data on the topic is scarce. So I challenged myself to come up with some data to satisfy my curiosity.
Next I show some of the data I collected from Scala projects using sbt, the most popular Scala build tool.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Informal introduction</title>
      <link>https://jvican.github.io/post/introduction/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Mar 2017 23:29:12 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jvican.github.io/post/introduction/</guid>
      <description>Hello, I am Jorge. I hack on Scala dev tools at the Scala Center. Read on me here.
In this blog I talk about computers and software. From time to time, you may find me discussing about other fields: mathematics, game theory, behavioral economics, literature or philosophy &amp;ndash; but with less likelihood.
If you like my work, spread the word. That&amp;rsquo;s a good way to say thanks.
If you want to reach out to me, check the footer of this website or head yourself to the About page.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>